<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Store Half Byte-Reverse Indexed</title><link>https://sthbrx.github.io/</link><description>A Power Technical Blog</description><atom:link href="https://sthbrx.github.io/feeds/rashmica-gupta.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 22:22:00 +1000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Interning at Ozlabs</title><link>https://sthbrx.github.io/blog/2016/06/08/interning-at-ozlabs/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I am sadly coming to the end of my six(ish) month internship with Ozlabs (funded by &lt;a href="https://www.acs.org.au"&gt;ACS&lt;/a&gt;). So here I am writing about my experience in the hopes that future prospective interns can read about how they should come and work with the previously dubbed Linux Gods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is your background?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite embracing being a nerd at school, my opinion of computers prior to starting my Engineering degree was that they were boring and for geeky boys who didn't want to interact with the 'real' world. However when having to choose a specialisation of Engineering I was drawn towards Computer Systems as everything else seemed obvious * but Computer Systems was this great mystical unknown. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward three years, and I had seen glimpses into the workings of this magical computer world. I had learnt about transistors, logic gates and opamps; I had designed circuits that actually worked; and I had bashed my head against a wall trying to find obscure bugs. I had dabbled in a range of languages from the low levels of VHDL and embedded C, to the abstract world of Python and Java and delved into the obscure world of declarative prologs and relational reinforcement learning. Now it was time to solidify some of these concepts and get some experience under my belt so I could feel less like a monkey bashing random keys on my keyboard. Enter Ozlabs!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What did you do at Ozlabs?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After being handed a nice laptop and the root passwords, I faced the inevitable battle of getting everything setup. With the help of my mentor, the prestigious &lt;a href="http://mpe.github.io/"&gt;Michael Ellerman&lt;/a&gt;, and various other Ozlabs residents I picked off some low hanging fruit such as removing unused code and tidying up a few things. This allowed me to get familiar with the open-source workflow, the kernel building process, IRC, do more with Git then just push and pull, and &lt;strong&gt;finally&lt;/strong&gt; come face-to-face with the seemingly impossible: Vim and virtual machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then got to learn about Transactional Memory (TM) - a way of making a bunch of instructions on one processor appear to be one atomic operation to other processors. I took some old TM tests from Mikey and checked that they did indeed pass and fail when they were supposed to and refurbished them a little, learning how to run kernel self-tests and a bit about powerpc assembly along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually my fear of shell scripts was no match for my desire to be able to build and install a kernel with one command and so I finally got around to writing a build script. Accidentally rebooting a bare-metal machine instead of my VM running on it may have had a significant contribution to this...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next interesting task I got to tackle was to implement a virtual memory dump that other architectures like x86 have, so we can see how the pages in memory are laid out along with information about these pages. This involved understanding x86's implementation and relating that to POWER's memory management. At Uni I never quite understood the fuss about pages and virtual memory and so it was great to be able to build up an appreciation and play around with page tables, virtual to real addresses, and hashtable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then moved onto &lt;a href="https://sthbrx.github.io/blog/2016/05/13/srop-mitigation/"&gt;SROP mitigation&lt;/a&gt;! After a lot of reading and re-reading, I decided to first understand how to use SROP to make an exploit on POWER which meant some assembly, diving into the signal code and finally meeting and spending time with GDB.  Once again I had x86 code to port over to POWER, the main issue being making sure that I didn't break existing things - aka hours and hours of running the kernel self-tests and the Linux Test Project tests and some more scripting, with the help of &lt;a href="http://blog.christophersmart.com/"&gt;Chris Smart&lt;/a&gt;, to collate the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can judge all my submitted patches &lt;a href="https://patchwork.ozlabs.org/project/linuxppc-dev/list/?submitter=67695&amp;amp;state=*"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What was your overall experience like at Ozlabs?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I moved to Canberra shortly after finishing exams and so hadn't had the time to ponder expectations of Ozlabs. Everyone was super friendly and despite being, not just the only female but, the only kiwi among a whoooole lot of Aussies I experienced a distinct lack of discrimination (apart from a bit of banter about accents).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could I wear my normal clothes (and not stuffy business clothes)? Check. Did I get to work on interesting things? Check. Could I do my work without having to go through lots of unnecessary hoops and what not? Check. Could I develop my own workflow and learn all the things? Check. Did I get to delve into a few different areas? Check. Was I surrounded by super smart people who were willing to help me learn? Check. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, I have had a great time here, learnt so much and you should definitely come and work at Ozlabs! Hopefully you'll see me back on this blog in a few months :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* &lt;em&gt;My pre-university, perhaps somewhat naiive, opinion: Civil and Mechanical is just physics. Chemical and Materials is just chemistry. Electrical seems interesting but who wants to work with power lines? Biomedical is just math and biology. Software is just abstract high level nonsense. But how a computer works?? That is some magical stuff.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Rashmica Gupta</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 22:22:00 +1000</pubDate><guid>tag:sthbrx.github.io,2016-06-08:blog/2016/06/08/interning-at-ozlabs/</guid><category>intern</category><category>experience</category></item><item><title>SROP Mitigation</title><link>https://sthbrx.github.io/blog/2016/05/13/srop-mitigation/</link><description>&lt;h2&gt;What is SROP?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sigreturn Oriented Programming - a general technique that can be used as an exploit, or as a backdoor to exploit another vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Okay, but what is it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah... Let me take you through some relevant background info, where I skimp on the details and give you the general picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Linux, software interrupts are called signals. More about signals &lt;a href="http://www.thegeekstuff.com/2012/03/linux-signals-fundamentals/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;! Generally a signal will convey some information from the kernel and so most signals will have a specific signal handler (some code that deals with the signal) setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Signals are asynchronous - ie they can be sent to a process/program at anytime. When a signal arrives for a process, the kernel suspends the process. The kernel then saves the 'context' of the process - all the general purpose registers (GPRs), the stack pointer, the next-instruction pointer etc - into a structure called a 'sigframe'. The sigframe is stored on the stack, and then the kernel runs the signal handler. At the very end of the signal handler, it calls a special system call called 'sigreturn' - indicating to the kernel that the signal has been dealt with. The kernel then grabs the sigframe from the stack, restores the process's context and resumes the execution of the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the rough mental picture you should have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Double Format" src="/images/rashmica/picture.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Okay... but you still haven't explained what SROP is..?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, if you insist...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above process was designed so that the kernel does not need to keep track of what signals it has delivered. The kernel assumes that the sigframe it takes off the stack was legitimately put there by the kernel because of a signal. This is where we can trick the kernel!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we can construct a fake sigframe, put it on the stack, and call sigreturn, the kernel will assume that the sigframe is one it put there before and will load the contents of the fake context into the CPU's registers and 'resume' execution from where the fake sigframe tells it to. And that is what SROP is!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Well that sounds cool, show me!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Firstly&lt;/strong&gt; we have to set up a (valid) sigframe:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By valid sigframe, I mean a sigframe that the kernel will not reject. Luckily most architectures only examine a few parts of the sigframe to determine the validity of it. Unluckily, you will have to dive into the source code to find out which parts of the sigframe you need to set up for your architecture. Have a look in the function which deals with the syscall sigreturn (probably something like sys_sigreturn() ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a real time signal on a little endian powerpc 64bit machine, the sigframe looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;rt_sigframe&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ucontext&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;uc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="kt"&gt;unsigned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;long&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;_unused&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;];&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="kt"&gt;unsigned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;tramp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;TRAMP_SIZE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;];&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;siginfo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;__user&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;pinfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="kt"&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;__user&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;puc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;siginfo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;info&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="kt"&gt;unsigned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;long&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;user_cookie&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* New 64 bit little-endian ABI allows redzone of 512 bytes below sp */&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="kt"&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;abigap&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;USER_REDZONE_SIZE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;];&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;__attribute__&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;aligned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The most important part of the sigframe is the context or ucontext as this contains all the register values that will be written into the CPU's registers when the kernel loads in the sigframe. To minimise potential issues we can copy valid values from the current GPRs into our fake ucontext:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;register&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;unsigned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;long&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;asm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;r1&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;register&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;unsigned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;long&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r13&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;asm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;r13&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ucontext&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ctx&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* We need a system thread id so copy the one from this process */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;ctx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;uc_mcontext&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;gp_regs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;PT_R13&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r13&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/*  Set the context&amp;#39;s stack pointer to where the current stack pointer is pointing */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;ctx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;uc_mcontext&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;gp_regs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;PT_R1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We also need to tell the kernel where to resume execution from. As this is just a test to see if we can successfully get the kernel to resume execution from a fake sigframe we will just point it to a function that prints out some text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* Set the next instruction pointer (NIP) to the code that we want executed */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;ctx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;uc_mcontext&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;gp_regs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;PT_NIP&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;unsigned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;long&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;test_function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For some reason the sys_rt_sigreturn() on little endian powerpc 64bit checks the endianess bit of the ucontext's MSR register, so we need to set that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* Set MSR bit if LE */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;ctx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;uc_mcontext&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;gp_regs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;PT_MSR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mh"&gt;0x01&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fun fact: not doing this or setting it to 0 results in the CPU switching from little endian to big endian! For a powerpc machine sys_rt_sigreturn() only examines ucontext, so we do not need to set up a full sigframe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Secondly&lt;/strong&gt; we have to put it on the stack:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* Set current stack pointer to our fake context */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;r1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;unsigned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;long&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ctx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thirdly&lt;/strong&gt;, we call sigreturn:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* Syscall - NR_rt_sigreturn */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;asm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;li 0, 172&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;asm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;sc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When the kernel receives the sigreturn call, it looks at the userspace stack pointer for the ucontext and loads this in. As we have put valid values in the ucontext, the kernel assumes that this is a valid sigframe that it set up earlier and loads the contents of the ucontext in the CPU's registers "and resumes" execution of the process from the address we pointed the NIP to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, you need something worth executing at this address, but sadly that next part is not in my job description. This is a nice gateway into the kernel though and would pair nicely with another kernel vulnerability.  If you are interested in some more in depth examples, have a read of &lt;a href="http://www.cs.vu.nl/~herbertb/papers/srop_sp14.pdf"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So how can we mitigate this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I'm glad you asked. We need some way of distinguishing between sigframes that were put there legitimately by the kernel and 'fake' sigframes. The current idea that is being thrown around is cookies, and you can see the x86 discussion &lt;a href="https://lkml.org/lkml/2016/3/29/788"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed solution is to give every sighand struct a randomly generated value. When the kernel constructs a sigframe for a process, it stores a 'cookie' with the sigframe. The cookie is a hash of the cookie's location and the random value stored in the sighand struct for the process. When the kernel receives a sigreturn, it hashes the location where the cookie should be with the randomly generated number in sighand struct - if this matches the cookie, the cookie is zeroed,  the sigframe is valid and the kernel will restore this context.  If the cookies do not match, the sigframe is not restored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Potential issues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multithreading: Originally the random number was suggested to be stored in the task struct. However, this would break multi-threaded applications as every thread has its own task struct. As the sighand struct is shared by threads, this should not adversely affect multithreaded applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cookie location: At first I put the cookie on top of the sigframe. However some code in userspace assumed that all the space between the signal handler and the sigframe  was essentially up for grabs and would zero the cookie before I could read the cookie value. Putting the cookie below the sigframe was also a no-go due to the ABI-gap (a gap below the stack pointer that signal code cannot touch) being a part of the sigframe. Putting the cookie inside the sigframe, just above the ABI gap has been fine with all the tests I have run so far!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Movement of sigframe: If you move the sigframe on the stack, the cookie value will no longer be valid... I don't think that this is something that you should be doing, and have not yet come across a scenario that does this. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a more in-depth explanation of SROP, click &lt;a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/676803/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Rashmica Gupta</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2016 22:22:00 +1000</pubDate><guid>tag:sthbrx.github.io,2016-05-13:blog/2016/05/13/srop-mitigation/</guid><category>SROP</category><category>mitigation</category><category>powerpc</category><category>kernel</category></item></channel></rss>