<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Store Half Byte-Reverse Indexed</title><link>https://sthbrx.github.io/</link><description>A Power Technical Blog</description><atom:link rel="self" href="https://sthbrx.github.io/feeds/russell-currey.rss.xml"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2016 15:33:00 +1000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Introducing snowpatch: continuous integration for patches</title><link>https://sthbrx.github.io/blog/2016/06/15/introducing-snowpatch-continuous-integration-for-patches/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Continuous integration has changed the way we develop software.  The ability to make a code change and be notified quickly and automatically whether or not it works allows for faster iteration and higher quality.  These processes and technologies allow products to quickly and consistently release new versions, driving continuous improvement to their users.  For a web app, it's all pretty simple: write some tests, someone makes a pull request, you build it and run the tests.  Tools like GitHub, Travis CI and Jenkins have made this process simple and efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's throw some spanners in the works.  What if instead of a desktop or web application, you're dealing with an operating system?  What if your tests can only be run when booted on physical hardware? What if instead of something like a GitHub pull request, code changes were sent as plain-text emails to a mailing list?  What if you didn't have control the development of this project, and you had to work with an existing, open community?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are some of the problems faced by the Linux kernel, and many other open source projects.  Mailing lists, along with tools like &lt;code&gt;git send-email&lt;/code&gt;, have become core development infrastructure for many large open source projects.  The idea of sending code via a plain-text email is simple and well-defined, not reliant on a proprietary service, and uses universal, well-defined technology.  It does have shortcomings, though.  How do you take a plain-text patch, which was sent as an email to a mailing list, and accomplish the continuous integration possibilities other tools have trivially?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of this problem birthed &lt;a href="https://github.com/ruscur/snowpatch"&gt;snowpatch&lt;/a&gt;, a continuous integration tool designed to enable these practices for projects that use mailing lists and plain-text patches.  By taking patch metadata organised by &lt;a href="https://patchwork.ozlabs.org"&gt;Patchwork&lt;/a&gt;, performing a number of &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; operations and shipping them off to &lt;a href="https://jenkins.io"&gt;Jenkins&lt;/a&gt;, snowpatch can enable continuous integration for any mailing list-based project.  At IBM &lt;a href="https://ozlabs.org"&gt;OzLabs&lt;/a&gt;, we're using snowpatch to automatically test new patches for &lt;a href="https://github.com/linuxppc/linux/"&gt;Linux on POWER&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/open-power/skiboot.git"&gt;skiboot&lt;/a&gt;, snowpatch itself, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;snowpatch is written in &lt;a href="https://rust-lang.org"&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt;, an exciting new systems programming language with a focus on speed and safety.  Rust's amazing software ecosystem, enabled by its package manager &lt;a href="https://crates.io"&gt;Cargo&lt;/a&gt;, made development of snowpatch a breeze.  Using Rust has been a lot of fun, along with the practical benefits of (in our experience) faster development, and confidence in the runtime stability of our code.  It's still a young language, but it's quickly growing and has an amazing community that has always been happy to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We still have a lot of ideas for snowpatch that haven't been implemented yet.  Once we've tested a patch and sent the results back to a patchwork instance, what if the project's maintainer (or a trusted contributor) could manually trigger some more intensive tests?  How would we handle it if the traffic on the mailing list of a project is too fast for us to test?  If we were running snowpatch on multiple machines on the same project, how would we avoid duplicating effort?  These are unsolved problems, and if you'd like to help us with these or anything else you think would be good for snowpatch, we take contributions and ideas via our mailing list, which you can subscribe to &lt;a href="https://lists.ozlabs.org/listinfo/snowpatch"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  For more details, view our documentation on &lt;a href="https://github.com/ruscur/snowpatch"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for taking your time to learn a bit about snowpatch.  In future, we'll be talking about how we tie all these technologies together to build a continuous integration workflow for the Linux kernel and OpenPOWER firmware.  Watch this space!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article was originally posted on &lt;a href="https://developer.ibm.com/open/"&gt;IBM developerWorks Open&lt;/a&gt;.  Check that out for more open source from IBM, and look out for more content in their &lt;a href="https://developer.ibm.com/open/snowpatch"&gt;snowpatch&lt;/a&gt; section.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Russell Currey</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2016 15:33:00 +1000</pubDate><guid>tag:sthbrx.github.io,2016-06-15:blog/2016/06/15/introducing-snowpatch-continuous-integration-for-patches/</guid><category>snowpatch</category><category>development</category><category>tools</category></item><item><title>Using the Atom editor for Linux kernel development</title><link>https://sthbrx.github.io/blog/2016/06/07/using-the-atom-editor-for-linux-kernel-development/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://atom.io"&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt; is a text editor.  It's new, it's shiny, and it has a lot of good and bad sides.  I work in a lab full of kernel developers, and in the kernel, there are no IDEs.  There's no real metadata you can get out of your compiler (given the kernel isn't very clang friendly), there's certainly nothing like that you can get out of your build system, so "plain old" text editors reign supreme.  It's a vim or Emacs show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so Atom comes along.  Unlike other shiny new text editors to emerge in the past 10 or so years, it's open source (unlike Sublime Text), it works well on Linux, and it's very configurable.  When it first came out, Atom was an absolute mess.  There was a noticeable delay whenever you typed a key.  That has gone, but the sour impression that comes from replacing a native application with a web browser in a frame remains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the curious person I am, I'm always trying out new things to see if they're any good.  I'm not particularly tied to any editor; I prefer modal editing, but I'm no vim wizard.  I eventually settled on using Emacs with evil-mode (which I assumed would make both Emacs and vim people like me, but the opposite happened), which was decent.  It was configurable, it was good, but it had issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Atom editor" src="/images/ruscur/36lOiMT.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let's have a look at how Atom stacks up for low-level work.  First of all, it's X only.  You wouldn't use it to change one line of a file in /etc/, and a lot of kernel developers only edit code inside a terminal emulator.  Most vim people do this since gvim is a bit wonky, and Emacs people can double-dip; using Emacs without X for small things and Emacs with X for programming.  You don't want to do that with Atom, if nothing else because of its slow startup time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let's look at configurability.  In my opinion, no editor will ever match the level of configurability of Emacs, however the barrier to entry is much lower here.  Atom has lots of options exposed in a config file, and you can set them there or you can use an equivalent GUI.  In addition, a perk of being a browser in a frame is that you can customise a lot of UI things with CSS, for those inclined.  Overall, I'd say Emacs &amp;gt; Atom &amp;gt; vim here, but for a newbie, it's probably Atom &amp;gt; Emacs &amp;gt; vim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, package management.  Atom is the clear winner here.  The package repository is very easy to use, for users and developers.  I wrote my own package, typed &lt;code&gt;apm publish&lt;/code&gt; and within a minute a friend could install it.  For kernel development though, you don't really need to install anything, Atom is pretty batteries-included.  This includes good syntax highlighting, ctags support, and a few themes.  In this respect, Atom feels like an editor that was created this century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Atom's inbuilt package management" src="/images/ruscur/DAx7GqD.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about actually editing text?  Well, I only use modal editing, and Atom is very far from being the best vim.  I think evil-mode in Emacs is the best vim, followed closely by vim itself.  Atom has a vim-mode, and it's fine for insert/normal/visual mode, but anything involving a : is a no-go.  There's a plugin that's entirely useless.  If I tried to do a replacement with :s, Atom would lock up &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; fail to replace the text.  vim replaced thousands of occurrences with in a second.  Other than that, Atom's pretty good.  I can move around pretty much just as well as I could in vim or Emacs, but not quite.  Also, it support ligatures!  The first kernel-usable editor that does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Autocompletions feel very good in Atom.  It completes within a local scope automatically, without any knowledge of the type of file you're working on.  As far as intelligence goes, Atom's support for tags outside of ctags is very lacking, and ctags is stupid.  Go-to definition &lt;em&gt;sometimes&lt;/em&gt; works, but it lags when dealing with something as big as the Linux kernel.  Return-from definition is very good, though.  Another downside is that it can complete from any open buffer, which is a huge problem if you're writing Rust in one tab and C in the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Atom's fuzzy file matching is pretty good" src="/images/ruscur/0PRiIUS.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An experience I've had with Atom that I haven't had with other editors is actually writing a plugin.  It was really easy, mostly because I stole a lot of it from an existing plugin, but it was easy.  I wrote a syntax highlighting package for POWER assembly, which was much more fighting with regular expressions than it was fighting with anything in Atom.  Once I had it working, it was very easy to publish; just push to GitHub and run a command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, Atom can get too clever for its own good.  For some completely insane reason, it automatically "fixes" whitespace in every file you open, leading to a huge amount of git changes you didn't intend.  That's easy to disable, but I don't want my editor doing that, it'd be much better if it highlighted whitespace it didn't like by default, like you can get vim and Emacs to do.  For an editor designed around git, I can't comprehend that decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Atom can also fuzzy match its commands" src="/images/ruscur/arbWXHx.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of git, the editor pretty much has everything you'd expect for an editor written at GitHub.  The sidebar shows you what lines you've added, removed and modified, and the gutter shows you what branch you're on and how much you've changed all-up.  There's no in-built support for doing git things inside the editor, but there's a package for it.  It's pretty nice to get something "for free" that you'd have to tinker with in other editors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, Atom has come a long way and still has a long way to go.  I've been using it for a few weeks and I'll continue to use it.  I'll encourage new developers to use it, but it needs to be better for experienced programmers who are used to their current workflow to consider switching.  If you're in the market for a new editor, Atom might just be for you.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Russell Currey</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2016 17:03:00 +1000</pubDate><guid>tag:sthbrx.github.io,2016-06-07:blog/2016/06/07/using-the-atom-editor-for-linux-kernel-development/</guid><category>education</category><category>kernel</category><category>development</category><category>tools</category></item><item><title>The Elegance of the Plaintext Patch</title><link>https://sthbrx.github.io/blog/2016/03/22/the-elegance-of-the-plaintext-patch/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I've only been working on the Linux kernel for a few months.  Before that, I worked with proprietary source control at work and common tools like GitHub at home.  The concept of the mailing list seemed obtuse to me.  If I noticed a problem with some program, I'd be willing to open an issue on GitHub but not to send an email to a mailing list.  Who still uses those, anyway?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting out with the kernel meant I had to figure this email thing out.  &lt;code&gt;git format-patch&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;git send-email&lt;/code&gt; take most of the pain out of formatting and submitting a patch, which is nice.  The patch files generated by &lt;code&gt;format-patch&lt;/code&gt; open nicely in Emacs by default, showing all whitespace and letting you pick up any irregularities.  &lt;code&gt;send-email&lt;/code&gt; means you can send it to yourself or a friend first, finding anything that looks stupid before being exposed to the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then what?  You've sent an email.  It gets sent to hundreds or thousands of people.  Nowhere near that many will read it.  Some might miss it due to their mail server going down, or the list flagging your post as spam, or requiring moderation.  Some recipients will be bots that archive mail on the list, or publish information about the patch.  If you haven't formatted it correctly, someone will let you know quickly.  If your patch is important or controversial, you'll have all sorts of responses.  If your patch is small or niche, you might not ever hear anything back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember when I sent my first patch.  I was talking to a former colleague who didn't understand the patch/mailing list workflow at all.  I sent him a link to my patch on a mail archive.  I explained it like a pull request - here's my code, you can find the responses.  What's missing from a GitHub-esque pull request?  We don't know what tests it passed.  We don't know if it's been merged yet, or if the maintainer has looked at it.  It takes a bit of digging around to find out who's commented on it.  If it's part of a series, that's awkward to find out as well.  What about revisions of a series?  That's another pain point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, these problems do have solutions.  &lt;a href="http://jk.ozlabs.org/projects/patchwork/"&gt;Patchwork&lt;/a&gt;, written by fellow OzLabs member &lt;a href="http://jk.ozlabs.org"&gt;Jeremy Kerr&lt;/a&gt;, changes the way we work with patches.  Project maintainers rely on Pathwork instances, such as &lt;a href="https://patchwork.ozlabs.org"&gt;https://patchwork.ozlabs.org&lt;/a&gt;, for their day-to-day workflow: tagging reviewers, marking the status of patches, keeping track of tests, acks, reviews and comments in one place.  Missing from this picture is support for series and revisions, which is a feature that's being developed by the &lt;a href="https://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/"&gt;freedesktop&lt;/a&gt; project.  You can check out their changes in action &lt;a href="https://patchwork.freedesktop.org"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, Patchwork helps patches and email catch up to what GitHub has in terms of ease of information.  We're still missing testing and other hooks.  What about review?  What can we do with email, compared to GitHub and the like?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, the biggest feature of email is the ease of review.  Just reply inline and you're done.  There's inline commenting on GitHub and GitLab, which works well but is a bit tacky, people commenting on the same thing overlap and conflict, each comment generates a notification (which can be an email until you turn that off).  Plus, since it's email, it's really easy to bring in additional people to the conversation as necessary.  If there's a super lengthy technical discussion in the kernel, it might just take Linus to resolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are alternatives to just replying to email, too, such as &lt;a href="https://www.gerritcodereview.com/"&gt;Gerrit&lt;/a&gt;.  Gerrit's pretty popular, and has a huge amount of features.  I understand why people use it, though I'm not much of a fan.  Reason being, it doesn't add to the email workflow, it replaces it.  Plaintext email is supported on pretty much any device, with a bunch of different programs.  From the goals of Patchwork: "patchwork should supplement mailing lists, not replace them".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linus Torvalds famously explained why he prefers email over GitHub pull requests &lt;a href="https://github.com/torvalds/linux/pull/17"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, using &lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/linux.kernel/w957vpu3PPU"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; pull request from Ben Herrenschmidt as an example of why git's own pull request format is superior to that of GitHub.  Damien Lespiau, who is working on the freedesktop Patchwork fork, &lt;a href="http://damien.lespiau.name/2016/02/augmenting-mailing-lists-with-patchwork.html"&gt;outlines on his blog&lt;/a&gt; all the issues he has with mailing list workflows and why he thinks mailing lists are a relic of the past.  His work on Patchwork has gone a long way to help fix those problems, however I don't think mailing lists are outdated and superceded, I think they are timeless.  They are a technology-agnostic, simple and free system that will still be around if GitHub dies or alienates its community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, there's still the case of the missing features.  What about automated testing?  What about developer feedback?  What about making a maintainer's life easier?  We've been working on improving these issues, and I'll outline how we're approaching them in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Russell Currey</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2016 13:53:00 +1100</pubDate><guid>tag:sthbrx.github.io,2016-03-22:blog/2016/03/22/the-elegance-of-the-plaintext-patch/</guid><category>development</category><category>education</category><category>kernel</category><category>patches</category></item><item><title>Panic, flushing and compromise</title><link>https://sthbrx.github.io/blog/2016/02/15/panic/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This is a tale of a simple problem, with a relatively simple solution, that ended up being pretty complicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The BMC of OpenPOWER machines expose a serial console.  It's pretty useful for getting information as the system is booting, or when it's having issues and the network is down.  OpenPOWER machines also have runtime firmware, namely &lt;a href="https://github.com/open-power/skiboot"&gt;skiboot&lt;/a&gt;, which the Linux kernel calls to make certain things happen.  One of those is writing to the serial console.  There's a function that &lt;a href="https://github.com/open-power/skiboot/blob/master/core/opal.c"&gt;skiboot exposes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;code&gt;opal_poll_events()&lt;/code&gt; (which then calls &lt;code&gt;opal_run_pollers()&lt;/code&gt;), which the kernel calls frequently.  Among other things, it performs a partial flush of the serial console.  And that all works fine...until the kernel panics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the kernel is in panic.  Who cares if it flushes the console?  It's dead.  It doesn't need to do anything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, right.  It prints the reason it panicked.  Turns out that's pretty useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a pretty simple fix here that we can push into the firmware.  Most kernels are configured to reboot after panic, typically with some delay.  In OpenPOWER, the kernel reboots by calling into skiboot with the &lt;code&gt;opal_cec_reboot()&lt;/code&gt; function.  So all we need to do is flush out the console buffer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;int64&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;opal_cec_reboot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;void&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;printf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;OPAL: Reboot request...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="n"&gt;console_complete_flush&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;();&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// &amp;lt;-- what I added&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// rebooting stuff happens here...&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;OPAL_SUCCESS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing a complete flushing function was pretty easy, then call it from the power down and reboot functions.  Easy, all nicely contained in firmware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, what if the kernel isn't configured to reboot after panic.  Or, what if the reboot timer is really long?  Do you want to wait 3 minutes to see your panic output?  Probably not.  We need to call the pollers after panic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I had to figure out what the kernel actually &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; when it panics.  Let's have a look at the &lt;a href="https://github.com/torvalds/linux/blob/master/kernel/panic.c"&gt;panic function itself&lt;/a&gt; to figure out where we could work some code in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;code&gt;panic()&lt;/code&gt; function, the easiest place I found to put in some code was &lt;code&gt;panic_blink()&lt;/code&gt;.  This is supposed to be a function to blink the LEDs on your keyboard when the kernel is panicking, but we could set it to &lt;code&gt;opal_poll_events()&lt;/code&gt; and it'd work fine.  There, problem solved!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, wait.  That will never get accepted upstream, ever.  Let's try again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, there are &lt;code&gt;#ifdef&lt;/code&gt;s in the code that are architecture specific, for s390 and SPARC.  I could add an &lt;code&gt;#ifdef&lt;/code&gt; to check if we're an OpenPOWER machine, and if so, run the pollers a bunch of times.  That would also involve including architecture specific code from &lt;code&gt;arch/powerpc&lt;/code&gt;, and that's somewhat gross.  Maybe I could upstream this, but it'd be difficult.  There must be a better way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a kernel noob, I found myself digging into what every function called by &lt;code&gt;panic()&lt;/code&gt; actually did, to see if there's a way I could use it.  I looked over it at first, but eventually I started looking harder at this line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class="n"&gt;kmsg_dump&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;KMSG_DUMP_PANIC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It turns out &lt;code&gt;kmsg_dump()&lt;/code&gt; does what it says: dumps messages from the kernel.  Different parts of the kernel can register their own dumpers, so the kernel can have a variety of dumpers for different purposes.  One existing example in OpenPOWER is a kmsg dumper that stores messages in &lt;code&gt;nvram&lt;/code&gt; (non-volatile RAM), so you can find it after you reboot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, we don't really want to dump any output, it's already been sent to the output buffer.  We just need to flush it.  Pretty simple, just call &lt;code&gt;opal_poll_events()&lt;/code&gt; a whole bunch of times, right?  That &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; work, though it'd be nice to have a better way than just calling the pollers.  Instead, we can add a new API call to skiboot specifically for console flushing, and call it from the kmsg dumper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, I wired up the skiboot complete console flushing function to a new OPAL API call, and called that from the kernel.  After some feedback, this was refactored into a partial, incremental flush so it was more generic.  I also had to consider what happened if the machine was running a newer kernel and an older skiboot, so if the skiboot version didn't have my new flushing call it would fall back to calling the pollers an arbitrary amount of times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, it looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/*&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt; * Console output is controlled by OPAL firmware.  The kernel regularly calls&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt; * OPAL_POLL_EVENTS, which flushes some console output.  In a panic state,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt; * however, the kernel no longer calls OPAL_POLL_EVENTS and the panic message&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt; * may not be completely printed.  This function does not actually dump the&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt; * message, it just ensures that OPAL completely flushes the console buffer.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt; */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;force_opal_console_flush&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;kmsg_dumper&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dumper&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                                     &lt;span class="k"&gt;enum&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;kmsg_dump_reason&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;reason&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int64_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ret&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="cm"&gt;/*&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;     * Outside of a panic context the pollers will continue to run,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;     * so we don&amp;#39;t need to do any special flushing.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;     */&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;reason&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;KMSG_DUMP_PANIC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;opal_check_token&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;OPAL_CONSOLE_FLUSH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;ret&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;opal_console_flush&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ret&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;OPAL_UNSUPPORTED&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;||&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ret&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;OPAL_PARAMETER&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* Incrementally flush until there&amp;#39;s nothing left */&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;opal_console_flush&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;OPAL_SUCCESS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="cm"&gt;/*&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;         * If OPAL_CONSOLE_FLUSH is not implemented in the firmware,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;         * the console can still be flushed by calling the polling&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;         * function enough times to flush the buffer.  We don&amp;#39;t know&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;         * how much output still needs to be flushed, but we can be&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;         * generous since the kernel is in panic and doesn&amp;#39;t need&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;         * to do much else.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;         */&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;printk&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;KERN_NOTICE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;opal: OPAL_CONSOLE_FLUSH missing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1024&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="n"&gt;opal_poll_events&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;NULL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can find the full code in-tree &lt;a href="https://github.com/torvalds/linux/blob/master/arch/powerpc/platforms/powernv/opal-kmsg.c"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And thus, panic messages now roam free 'cross the countryside, causing developer frustration around the world.  At least now they know why they're frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Russell Currey</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2016 14:23:00 +1100</pubDate><guid>tag:sthbrx.github.io,2016-02-15:blog/2016/02/15/panic/</guid></item></channel></rss>